<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
<!ENTITY zwsp "&#8203;">
<!ENTITY nbhy "&#8209;">
<!ENTITY wj "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" docName="draft-many-tiptop-ip-architecture-02" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IP in Deep Space">An Architecture for IP in Deep Space</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-many-tiptop-ip-architecture-02"/>
    <author fullname="Marc Blanchet" initials="MB">
      <organization>Viagenie</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>marc.blanchet@viagenie.ca</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Wesley Eddy" initials="WE">
      <organization>Aalyria Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>wes@aalyria.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Tony Li" initials="TL">
      <organization>Hewlett Packard Enterprise</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>tony.li@tony.li</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>dtn</keyword>
    <keyword>quic</keyword>
    <keyword>space</keyword>
    <keyword>deep space</keyword>
    <keyword>ip</keyword>
    <keyword>dns</keyword>
    <keyword>routing</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
	The IP protocol stacks used on Earth's Internet are
	typically configured based on assumptions of short delays and mostly uninterrupted
	communications. This document describes the architecture of the
	IP protocol stack tailored for its use in deep space. It
	involves buffering IP packets in IP forwarders facing
	intermittent links
	and adjusting transport protocol configurations and application
	protocol timers. This architecture applies to the Moon, Mars, and
	general interplanetary networking.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
        <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
	Deep-space communications involve long delays and intermittent connectivity due to the distances and orbital motion involved.  For instance,
            Earth to Mars transmissions vary 4-24 minutes, and are unavailable periodically due to rotation, conjunctions, and other conditions.
      </t>
      <t>Deep space communications 
      have traditionally been done on
      a layer-2 point-to-point basis, sometimes uing
      relays, but no layer-3 networking has been in routine use.
      <xref target="RFC4838"/> reports an assessment done around 25 years
      ago concluding that the IP protocol stack was not suitable for
      deep space networking. However, some things have changed since
      that time, as there has been evolution in multiple areas including Internet transport and
      security protocols (e.g. QUIC), routing (e.g. SDN), and forwarding
      technology (e.g. MPLS and Segment Routing), compression (e.g. SCHC), network management, and applications (e.g. HTTP and CoAP).
      </t>
      <t>Currently, space agencies have published plans that include deploying IP
      networks on celestial bodies, such as the Moon <xref target="ioag"/> and Mars <xref target="ioag-mars"/>, both on the
      surfaces and orbiting constellations, including link layer technologies such
      as Wi-Fi or 5G. On the surface, the plans involve dense
      networking around facilities and habitats.  New mission concepts are also including clusters of multiple networked nodes co-located at Lagrange points.</t>
      <t>
 Given the evolution of modern IP application protocol stacks and the new needs of deep space missions, this document describes an architecture for the use of IP in deep space, meeting needs described in <xref target="I-D.many-tiptop-usecase"/>.
 This includes:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>running IP over end-to-end paths that include
	high-latency, deep space layer-2 links,</li>
        <li>buffering of IP packets, when needed,</li>
        <li>IP addressing and routing,</li>
        <li>transport protocol configuration,</li>
        <li>application protocols,</li>
        <li>and other network services, including network
            management of deep space IP networks.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>An aspect of this framework is the potential for queueing outbound packets for upcoming
      contact opportunities.
      In this case, the IP layer has to deal with the fact that
      a next-hop may not be currently reachable and that IP packets
      could be buffered for an unusual amount of time, such as minutes,
      hours, or days in the forwarding device waiting for next-hop reachability or a
      link-up  opportunity. The transport layer should be able to work
      with long and variable delays, including intermittent
      communications. The application protocols and the applications
      themselves should be properly set to wait a longer time than on
      the current Internet to receive a response to a query. Finally, all network services such as routing, security, naming, and network management should also be adapted to this new context. This document is structured around these layers.  General architecture concerns are described along with suitable ways to address them.  Separate documents cover the details of configuring specific protocols, e.g. QUIC, in accordance with this framework.</t>
      <t>
    Applying the IP stack and its mature family of standards in
	deep space enables the reuse of many protocols, tools, and
	software currently used on the Internet. However,
	many components of the IP stack cannot be used
	as-is and require careful configuration and
	deployment considerations that are discussed in this document.
      </t>
      <t>
	Since the Moon is within a few light seconds away from Earth, it is
	possible to configure and run typical Internet protocols and
	applications to basically "work", however, Mars with a much longer delay
	is more difficult. The framework in this document covers both,
	and would also work for longer delays, such as reaching
    Jupiter or the whole Solar System.  The focus is on the Moon and Mars because those are where significant numbers of relevant missions are being developed presently.</t>
      <t>This document uses "deep space"
	extensively as opposed to "space", as that more generally includes other topics such as
      terrestrial satellite access, earth-orbiting, and near-Earth missions, which are not covered in this
      document, and subject of other RFCs (e.g. <xref target="RFC2488"/>, <xref target="RFC2760"/>, <xref target="RFC3135"/>, <xref target="RFC9717"/>).
      The scope of "deep space" in this document includes the Moon, although this is not strictly within the ITU's definition of the term.
      </t>

      <t>The key characteristics of space communications and networking, the relevant use case aspects and requirements are discussed in <xref target="I-D.many-tiptop-usecase"/>.</t>
      <section>
        <name>Document and Discussion Location</name>
        <t>The source of this document is located at https://github.com/marcblanchet/draft-tiptop-ip-architecture. Comments or changes are welcomed using a PR or an issue.</t>
        <t>This subject should be discussed on the deepspace@ietf.org mailing list of the Taking IP To Other Planets (TIPTOP) working group.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="layer2">
      <name>Layer 2 in Deep Space</name>
      <section anchor="layer2surface">
        <name>Celestial Body Surface</name>
        <t>The Interagency Operations Advisory Group (IOAG) <xref target="ioag"/> has defined the communications architecture
	for the Moon and Mars. On the celestial body surface, it is planned to use 3GPP and Wi-Fi link layer protocols. IP will be used over these link layers.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="layer2ccsds">
        <name>Deep Space Links</name>
        <t>Deep space links typically use the Consultative Committee
	for Space Data Standards (CCSDS) <xref target="CCSDSWEB"/>
	standards for link layers, such as Telecommand (TC) <xref target="CCSDS_TC"/>, Telemetry (TM) <xref target="CCSDS_TM"/>,
	Advanced Orbiting Systems (AOS) <xref target="CCSDS_AOS"/>,
	Proximity1 (Prox1) <xref target="CCSDS_PROX1"/> or the Unified
	Space Data Link Protocol (USLP) <xref target="CCSDS_USLP"/>. CCSDS has defined a generic
	encapsulation mechanism for the payloads for all these link
	layer protocols with IP as an encapsulated protocol
	<xref target="IPoverCCSDSSpaceLinks"/> <xref target="SANAIPEHeaderRegistry"/>. Therefore, IP packets can be transported over any CCSDS link layers.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="layer2orbit">
        <name>Celestial Body Orbits</name>
        <t>For celestial body orbits, IOAG has planned the use of CCSDS
	link layer protocols. However, as on Earth, it may be possible
	to use 6G-NTN technology around celestial bodies, such as in
	lunar or Martian orbits. 6G-NTN technologies use IP as its
	layer 3 technology.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ip">
      <name>Internet Protocol</name>
      <t>IPv4 or IPv6 packets can be carried as is over long delays
      and disruptions, as IP has no notion of time. Originally,
      the Time To Live (TTL) field of IPv4 was defined based on time
      <xref target="STD5"/>, but it has been effectively implemented
      as a hop count, which was renamed as "Hop Count" in IPv6 <xref target="STD86"/>. Nothing needs to be changed to the IP protocol or its packet format.</t>

      <t>
	The architecture described in this document can support IPv4
	and/or IPv6. While some may prefer one version or another,
	there are important considerations that complicate
	matters. Deep space links are very low bandwidth. The
	additional overhead of an IPv6 packet will have a bandwidth
	and performance impact that needs to be considered early in
	mission planning. From a future-proofing perspective, IPv6 is
	to be preferred.  Eventually, as technology evolves and the
	bandwidth constraints are relieved, we would greatly prefer to
	not have to retrofit existing, deployed spacecraft with
	IPv6. Ultimately, however, the IETF does not have authority
	over this decision. The various space agencies, working in
	unison, should make this joint decision and select one version
	for interopability.
      </t>
      <section>
        <name>IP Forwarding and Store-and-Forward</name>
        <t>
	  For deep space applications, an IP packet may need to be
	  queued for much longer periods than are typical
	  for the Internet when the next hop is currently unreachable
      or undefined, which can happen due to planning of periodic contacts
      around orbital dynamics, and other antenna scheduling limitations. Terms
      have been used including "store-and-forward" (which is already
      used differently elsewhere in the context of switch architectures), or
      "store, carry, and forward", to describe the behavior of buffering IP
      packets rather than immediately discarding them when the next-hop
      is not immediately available on-link.
        </t>
        <t>
	  This queuing may be implemented at layer
	  2 as is currently done by the Mars orbiters. In this case,
	  the frames are stored, regardless of payload type.  In this
	  case, IP packets are unaware of the store-and-forward and no
	  changes are needed in the IP forwarding function.  The L2
	  network is just behaving as a point-to-point link with a
	  large and variable latency.
	</t>
        <t>
	  If an IP forwarder has an interface on an intermittent link, and that link is down,
      some destinations may become unreachable when there is no alternate route. In this case,
	  the forwarder buffers the IP packets locally instead of dropping them. This might be implemented as a deep queue with
	  active queue management (AQM) <xref target="RFC7567"/>. When the
	  route to the destination is back, on the same link or a different link, maybe minutes or hours
	  later, the stored packets can be transmitted.
	</t>
        <t>
	  This requires proper
	  provisioning of buffer storage memory for the
	  target deployment and usage. If the buffer is full, then
      packets must be dropped. The choice of which packets
	  to drop depends on the policies configured on the node, which may be a
	  function of traffic class, source or destination IP
	  addresses, flow labels, or other parameters. An example is
	  described in <xref target="I-D.blanchet-tvr-forwarding"/>.
	</t>
        <t>Packets might also be lost if a buffer is cleared for any other reason (e.g. due to reboot), or corrupted somehow (e.g. due to cosmic rays or other uncorrectable memory upsets).  The architecture described in this document does not require IP forwarding nodes to necessarily implement anything beyond a typical "best effort" service and reliability, though more complex means to support reliable packet delivery are compatible and can interoperate within the architecture if desirable.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="headercompression">
        <name>Header Compression</name>
        <t>
	  Deep space links are point-to-point links and bandwidth in
	  space is very valuable, so header compression is very effective. Static Context Header Compression (SCHC) <xref target="I-D.ietf-schc-architecture"/> is a header
	  compression technique that relies on rules in a static
	  context and is, therefore, more efficient for deep
	  space. SCHC should be considered on a deep space
	  point-to-point link or a string of L2 links.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>IP Addressing and Routing</name>
      <section title="Addressing">
        <t>
      The IP address space is a hierarchical namespace where
      ranges of addresses are encoded as "prefixes".  Individual
      domains advertise prefixes to the broader Internet
      and assign these addresses internally. Prefixes may be
      aggregated into less-specific prefixes, which makes the
      routing subsystem more efficient by decreasing overhead.
    </t>
        <t>
      Space networks provide a unique opportunity to provide
      extremely efficient routing by assigning a unique prefix or
      block of addresses per celestial body and its proximal
      orbits. Management of the IP address space is currently
      documented in <xref target="RFC7020"/>, but this only covers
      continental regions and does not provide for addressing for
      space. The depletion of the IPv4 address space means that there
      is little than can be done if agencies decide to use
      IPv4.
    </t>
    <t>
      However, if agencies decide to utilize IPv6, it would be deeply
      beneficial if addressing was designed to allow for the maximum
      aggregation of routing prefixes. Aggregation of prefixes
      assigned to celestrial bodies would minimize the overhead
      incurred by relaying spacecraft, minimizing expensive hardware
      requirements and would help minimize route flap.  Thus, to help
      achieve maximum aggregation, the address space for outer space
      should be managed by a Regional Internet Registry (RIR) and
      blocks of address space should be allocated for each celestial
      body of interest. Space service providers should use prefixes
      assigned by this RIR. This is discussed in more detail in <xref
      target="I-D.li-tiptop-address-space"/>.
    </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Routing">
        <t>
	Existing routing protocols require proof of liveness between
	protocol partners, implemented through the periodic exchange
	of packets between partners. This is impractical on long-delay
	or intermittent links, so a Path Computation Engine (PCE)
	<xref target="RFC4655"/> based approach seems appropriate for
	those domains possibly supplemented by contact plan
	schedules<xref
	target="I-D.ietf-tvr-schedule-yang"/>. Interconnection between
	domains can still be done with BGP <xref target="RFC4271"/>,
	but long-delay or intermittent links should be
	avoided. Domains straddling such links must provide proxy
	advertisements for prefixes reachable across such links.
      </t>
        <t>
	Optimal routing for domains with intermittent links is out of
	scope for this document.
      </t>
        <t>
	On the surface of celestial bodies and in proximal orbit,
	traditional protocols are applicable and should be used (e.g.,
	<xref target="RFC9717"/>).
      </t>
      <t>
	Because of bandwidth limitations, the PCE for a domain may
	require the ability to specify an explicit path, but using an
	explicit path across an intermittent link may be
	problematic. If a packet is bound to an explicit path and
	stored in an intermediate node, then the path may be invalid
	at the end of the storage period. Conveying a backup path
	within the packet itself would incur a large performance
	penalty and is not recommended. Allowing the intermediate node
	itself to compute the remainder of the path would seem to be
	the most robust solution. Conventional traffic engineering
	techniques for getting to storage nodes seem to be
	appropropriate.
      </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Transport</name>
      <t>

Modern transport protocols and stacks share similar algorithms for common
transport needs.  This section first addresses general transport issues, and
then addresses use of specific individual transport protocols.  While there
have been academic research experiments in developing new protocols
specifically for interplanetary transport, they are not directly considered
here because the goal is to leverage IETF protocols and commonly available
software.

      </t>
      <section anchor="general-transport">
        <name>General Transport Issues</name>
        <t>

Internet transport protocols and transport stacks have developed to meet the
needs for different classes of applications on the terrestrial Internet, using
similar algorithms with parameters that are tuned for typical conditions.  Some
of these algorithms might simply be parameterized differently for interplanetary
network paths, while other algorithms may have fundamental challenges.  In some
cases, minor adjustments (or no adjustment) will suffice for Earth-lunar
networking.

        </t>
        <ul>
          <li><t>

Protocol Negotiation / "Happy Eyeballs" - Due to presence of both IPv4 and IPv6
in the terrestrial Internet, applications or transport stacks may include
"happy eyeballs" capabilities <xref target="RFC8305"/> that make use of
multiple DNS queries and connection attempts for different addresses and
address families returned.  Downsides to this in interplanetary applications
might include (1) the additional load on interplanetary DNS (although solutions
to this are avialable <xref target="I-D.many-tiptop-dns"/>), (2) unnecessary
use of network capacity for paralel connection attempts (e.g. if 0-RTT data
transmission is used), and (3) unnecessary additional transport state
maintained for an extended period of time.  If applications for interplanetary
use initially rely on either fixed IP addresses (instead of DNS names) or a
single address family (e.g. IPv6), then there should be no downsides to
presence of happy eyeballs algorithms within the transport stack.  If happy
eyeballs is present and triggered, then the values in section 8 of <xref
target="RFC8305"/> should be carefully considered and tuned based on the DNS
and path expectations (e.g. resolution delay, first address family count,
connection attmept delay, minimum connection attempt delay, and maximum
connection attempt delay) as most of these values are not likely to be
appropriate even for Earth-lunar paths.

          </t></li>
          <li><t>

Connection Initiation / Handshaking - Very long-lived connection state may be
used to avoid connection initiation in some cases, e.g. by establishing state
prior to launch and using those pre-established connections long-term.
However, this will not be possible in all cases for all applications, if flows
can't be planned pre-launch.  Due to the need to be robust to stale packets,
errors, and denial of service attacks, historically, Internet transports have
included handshaking
state machines, such as 3-way and 4-way handshakes for connection establishment
(the case can be even worse for some transport protocol and TLS combinations),
although QUIC can established secured connections with only 1 round-trip time.
Since the interplanetary round trip times may be larger than the duration of
contact periods, these handshaking mechanisms are very inefficient.  Though
they are tolerable in cases such as between Earth and lunar networks, they are
stifling for Earth-Mars and other interplanetary network paths.  Transports,
such as QUIC, that have the ability to resume based on shared state from prior
application connections or to rapidly start transferring data ("0RTT") can be
suitably efficient, once initial state is obtained; however, they still require
a complete initial handshake with the full set of round trip times imposed.
For interplanetary use, it may be beneficial to find ways to securely pre-set
information to allow this more efficient startup, without requiring the full
initial handshake even once.

          </t></li>
          <li><t>

Capability / Feature Negotiation - Ideally, transport protocol feature
advertisements and agreements can be completed prior to launch as part of
connection pre-establishment and cached long-term.  Any negotiation of
additional features that requires full round trip times is prohibitive for
general interplanetary use, especially if data transmission is stalled while
negotiation takes place.  Commonly, much negotiation can occur in the initial
connection handshake.  It will be beneficial if transport stacks can cache (or
securely pre-configure caches) of pre-negotiated features with typical hosts
that they plan to communicate with during the course of a mission.

          </t></li>
          <li><t>

Retransmission - Reliable transport protocols typically keep retransmission
timers, computed based on round trip time samples <xref target="RFC6298"/>
<xref target="RFC8961"/>.  Since it may be impossible to even take RTT
measurements within a contact window, and RTTs may vary significantly across
contact windows, this type of algorithm is not appropriate for interplanetar
use.  Additionally, default values may be in ranges such as 1 second, that are
inappropriate for even Earth-lunar paths.  Based on the known propagation times
for interplanetary paths and predicted contacts, either pre-configured values
or new algorithms should be used.

          </t></li> 
          <li><t>

Handling Failures - Aside from retransmission, there are also other types of
timers and counters in transport stacks, for things including DNS resolution,
connection establishment retries, connection keep-alives, user timeouts, and
delayed acknowledgement.  Additionally, transports receive and respond to ICMP
messages that indicate other different types of errors from within the network.
Similar to the case of retransmission timers, other types of timers that
support failure handling should be adjusted based on estimated propagation and
forwarding times.  Other heuristics for validating ICMP messages and responding
may need to be considered.

          </t></li>
          <li><t>

Congestion Control - Internet congestion control algorithms are based on timely
receipt of feedback in order to detect losses, delays, or other signals, and
typically attempt to react rapidly.  Two challenges in the interplanetary case
include: (1) The relative delays on interplanetary paths are much longer
(preventing "rapid" response) and may vary in orders of magnitude between
segments, e.g. across a terrestrial segment, an Earth-Mars segment, and a Mars
orbit/surface segment.  Congestion may occur in low-latency portions of the
network, but fail to be detected quickly because loss/acknowledgement
information propagates and feeds back too slowly, leading to sustained loss due
to unresponsiveness in a low-latency portion of the network.  (2) By the time
feedback is received, it is badly out of date, if not completely irrelevant to
the future.  The advent of IP-based in-network storage for scheduled
interplanetary links also changes the way that congestion can be measured (e.g.
in delay-based protocols).  In the near-term, and in present space mission
operations, it can be assumed that data link capacity is explicitly planned and
scheduled end-to-end in order to accomodate mission needs.  This makes
congestion control algorithms largely replaceable with simple nominal rate and
flow control.  However, for larger and more dynamic future interplanetary
networks, and shared trunk links, etc., it will be useful in the future to develop more
optimized congestion control methods, including possibly more effective
network-based signaling/feedback, rather than simply end-to-end feedback-based
mechanisms.

          </t></li>
          <li><t>

Path MTU Discovery - Internet transports typically include probing algorithms
and rely on end-to-end acknowledgements (or in legacy cases ICMP errors) in
order to infer the maximum packet sizes that can be used at any time without
introducing unnecessary IP fragmentation.  Because for interplanetary cases,
feedback may be slow or unrelated to the current or future paths by the time it
arrives, it may be more beneficial to simply rely on known / pre-arranged path
MTU limitations that can be communicated between interplanetary providers and
other connected providers and users.  Especially for higher bandwidth links, it
may be beneficial for this to be significantly larger than the minimum Internet
MTU values that are normally assumed.  For instance, terrestrially many systems
use 9000+ byte MTUs.  MTUs in interplanetary networks may vary due to the range
of link bandwidths, and simultaneous desires to be efficient on fast links
while also wanting to avoid head-of-line blocking for large packets on
low-bandwidth links.

          </t></li>
          <li><t>

Multiple Streams - Several transports allow for applications to send/receive
multiple independent streams of application data, rather than requiring
separate connections (and handshakes, and state) for each stream.  Due to the
need to leverage pre-established state and make efficient use of connectivity
opportunities, these capabilities can be valuable to leverage for
interplanetary use, however, specific mechanisms may need to be
evaluated/tuned/modified e.g. to avoid additional round trip times.

          </t></li>
          <li><t>

Multipath Transport - There may be a variety of different physical paths
between planets (e.g. using relays or direct links), that could be attractive
for a mission to use simultaneously as way to increase reliability for mission
data, or to increase throughput for an application.  However, typical Internet
multipath transport algorithms are oriented more towards failover than towards
replicating or load-balancing traffic.  They may only switch flows between
using alternative paths (e.g. for failover), or allow different streams to use
different paths, rather than replicating data.  For deep space use, Internet
multipath transport algorithms could either be tuned or replaced.

          </t></li>
          <li><t>

Forward Error Correction (FEC) - Generally, FEC is expected to be implemented
below the link layer.  Within the transport layer, FEC and/or erasure coding
are not common in typical Internet use today, though FEC and/or erasure coding
can be integrated with different protocol stacks.  Because it can allow for
data recovery in the case of packet losses, without suffering extra round
trips, or requiring bidirectional connectivity, this may be valuable to
incorporate/enable in future interplanetary transport stacks.

          </t></li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="udp">
        <name>UDP</name>
        <t>UDP <xref target="RFC768"/> has no notion of time and,
	therefore can be used as-is in deep space. Hence, protocols using UDP transport can be used in space as-is, if they do not rely on time or can be configured with timeouts appropriate in deep space.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="quic-section">
        <name>QUIC</name>
        <t>QUIC <xref target="RFC9000"/> like most IP transport protocols
	implements congestion control mechanisms, which, based on
	various metrics such as calculated delays or packet loss, pace
	the rate of sending packets at the source node to decrease the
	perceived congestion in the network. QUIC supports many new
	features suitable and useful in deep space such as 1 RTT for
	connection establishment and security, mobility, 0 RTT,
	streams, user space, etc. [TLI: This sentence needs more words
	to explain these references.]</t>
        <t>Current implementations of QUIC typically set various
	transport configuration parameters suitable for the Internet
	environment, expecting an RTT to be in the hundreds of milliseconds
	and a normally always-connected network. Therefore, QUIC
	stacks using default configurations will not work in deep
	space. However, studies and simulations <xref target="quic-sim"/> showed that with proper configuration of
	parameters, QUIC stacks can support the delays and disruptions
	in deep space. <xref target="I-D.many-deepspace-quic-profile"/> describes how to
	properly configure a QUIC stack for deep space applications,
	where QUIC is unaware of disruptions. If the transport is
	aware of the disruptions, further optimizations are possible.</t>
        <t>Having multiple streams and applications within a single
	QUIC connection is valuable and useful for deep space. A
	ground station may set up the initial QUIC connection with a spacecraft and then carry all needed applications and streams over that same connection for the whole duration of the mission.</t>
        <t>Session keys and certificate lifetimes together with certificate validation and trust chain anchors need to be carefully configured and handled.</t>
        <t>QUIC proxies <xref target="I-D.ietf-masque-quic-proxy"/>
	can be used at the edge of space to isolate, apply policies, or
	optimize traffic at the ingress/egress to a celestial body network.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Other Transports</name>
        <t>Other transports such as TCP <xref target="RFC9293"/>, SCTP
	<xref target="RFC9260"/>, DCCP <xref target="RFC4340"/> and others were not investigated for their suitability in space.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="http-section">
      <name>HTTP</name>
      <t>HTTP by itself has no notion of time. An HTTP request and
      response may take minutes or hours to be completed. However,
      current infrastructure and software on the Internet have various time-related configurations that will not work well in the deep space context.</t>
      <t>HTTP headers containing time, such as Cache-Control and
      Expires <xref target="RFC9111"/>, should not be used or if used,
      must be set to large enough values to cover the longest delay so
      that expiration does not happen before the actual data arrives
      at the destination. As with any HTTP application and content on
      the Internet, these headers should be set properly based on the
      deployment use case, which is even more important for deep
      space. Similarly, when continuous content transfer is used, as
      with 100-Continue <xref target="RFC9110"/>, proper values for
      headers should be set.</t>
      <t>HTTP clients and servers typically have default timeouts that
      should be modified. For example, curl <xref target="curl"/> has the "-m" option for this use
      case. Similarly, HTTP server implementations have various
      timeout configuration variables that must be set
      properly. Testing with HTTP client Curl and HTTP server nginx
      and an introduced network delay of minutes, hours and days showed<xref target="quic-sim"/> that HTTP
      communications work well with basic configuration changes.</t>
      <t>HTTP applications themselves must be developed using an asynchronous pattern and if they have timeouts, they should be adjusted appropriately.</t>
      <t>Internet websites are designed with the assumption of
      hundreds of milliseconds delay and relatively always connected,
      where pages contain multiple queries to get further resources,
      media, queries to web services, and downloading additional code
      and frameworks. This could work in theory in space, but it will
      not be optimal, as multiple queries will be generated and
      therefore take multiple RTT before the whole page is received
      complete. This issue can be mitigated by using various
      techniques such as Web Assembly <xref target="wasm"/> or
      pre-caching. Moreover, it could be possible to have simple HTML
      pages with no or very few references and no media content 
      that was not locally cached. An example would be a rover on Mars presenting an HTTP server with a base and bare HTML page to offer basic info on its status (maybe all in text) and some additional detailed pages, most likely also in base HTML text. However, it is foreseen that most applications based on QUIC-HTTP transport in deep space would be using REST or similar asynchronous patterns and not typical web browsing.</t>
      <t>Caching should be used extensively on space networks to maximize local fetching. Preemptive caching by pre-populating caches with data that shall be used locally on the celestial body network shall be done as much as possible to provide better response time on the local celestial body network.</t>
      <t>QPACK <xref target="RFC9204"/> should be considered for higher bandwidth efficiency.</t>
      
      <section>
          <name>CoAP</name>
          <t>The Constrained Application Protocol (CoAP)<xref target="RFC7252"/> is a specialized web transfer protocol for use with constrained nodes and constrained networks, therefore a candidate for an application protocol for space, similar to HTTP. If considered, proper use of its underlying transport and timers should be looked at.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Network services</name>
      <section anchor="dns">
        <name>Naming</name>
        <t>
	  For small-scale deployments, one can use IP addresses
	  directly or a mapping from a name to an IP address such as
	  /etc/hosts.  However, this does not provide easy dynamic
	  updates, scaling by hierarchy, service discovery,
	  authentication of records, etc. Therefore, the Domain Name
	  System (DNS) shall be considered early on in the space
	  deployment. However, naming hierarchy and infrastructure
	  must be carefully designed to avoid name resolution over
	  deep space links, given that answers may come after minutes
	  or hours. There are clear advantages of having the space
	  name hierarchy anchored to the current Internet root, as it
	  enables DNSSEC through the same security infrastructure
	  currently used and deployed. Using the same root also does
	  not require new policies. A new TLD or a new root is way
	  more complicated and does not bring any significant value
	  compared to using the current domain tree.</t>
        <t>Care must be taken to manage key lifecycles and resource
	record lifetimes. <xref target="I-D.many-dnsop-dns-isolated-networks"/> discusses the
	various methods and the naming hierarchy that should be used in space.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
          <name>Network Management</name>
          <t>NETCONF <xref target="RFC6241"/> and RESTCONF <xref target="RFC8040"/> shall be used with proper configuration
              values to avoid timeouts and appropriate transport. NETCONF
              over QUIC transport <xref target="I-D.ietf-netconf-over-quic"/> or RESTCONF over HTTP over QUIC transport shall be configured with appropriate QUIC transport parameters as discussed in <xref target="quic-section"/>.</t>
          <t>Given the non-typical delays in requests and response in space compared to traditional network management frameworks on Internet and private networks, expectations about when configuration changes will be applied and confirmed or the timeliness of the actual value received from a request need to be taken into account. For example, a configuration change may take hours to be received by the spacecraft, which is not expected in typical network operations. A request for some value may take hours to be received by the spacecraft and take hours to be received by the requestor, which means the value may not be current or expired. Moreover, typical timeouts of NETCONF clients should be adjusted to the expected RTT.</t>
          <t>While being declared historic in IETF, SNMP<xref target="RFC1157"/> runs over UDP and has no notion of time. Therefore, with proper configuration of client timeout, it can be used as is to manage nodes and services in deep space.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Using the current IP protocol stack in deep space inherits
      all the work on privacy, cryptography, key management,
      firewalls, and scrutiny of protocols that are deployed on the
      Internet. As an example, TLS has been more carefully examined
      than almost any other secure transport protocol. Moreover, given
      that no changes are made in the protocols, this architecture
      does not bring new security issues on the protocols themselves. Deep space security
      requirements are different than on the existing Internet, but nothing has been found to prevent the conformance of the IP protocol stack to those requirements.</t>
      <t>As it is currently planned, the deep space network shall be
      isolated from the current Internet by an "air gap", to disable
      any direct communications from the Internet to deep space. Moreover, destination IP prefix filtering shall be used to restrict the traffic to only the relevant one for each link. Note that this shall also be implemented in the routing control plane, but additional security might be appropriate to further protect the deep space links.</t>
      <t>Each celestial network edge device shall have firewall rules
      to prevent inappropriate traffic from entering deep space
      links. If communications from Mars may only occur to Earth, but
      not to the Moon, then appropriate filtering based on destination
      IP prefixes shall be used.</t>
      <t>Storage in IP forwarders may become full by normal traffic or by malicious traffic that could become a denial-of-service attack.
          Appropriate policies and measures should be put in place in those forwarders to drop packets in advance to avoid the depletion of storage space and to mitigate such attacks.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.768.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1157.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2488.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2760.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3135.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4340.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4838.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6298.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7020.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7252.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7567.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8040.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8305.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8961.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9000.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9110.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9111.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9204.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9260.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9293.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9717.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml9/reference.STD.0005.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml9/reference.STD.0086.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.blanchet-tvr-forwarding.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-masque-quic-proxy.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netconf-over-quic.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-schc-architecture.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tvr-schedule-yang.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.li-tiptop-address-space.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.many-deepspace-ip-assessment.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.many-tiptop-usecase.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.many-deepspace-quic-profile.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.many-dnsop-dns-isolated-networks.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.many-tiptop-dns.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="IPoverCCSDSSpaceLinks" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/702x1b1c2.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>IP OVER CCSDS SPACE LINKS, Blue Book 702</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2012" month="September"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="SANAIPEHeaderRegistry" target="https://sanaregistry.org/r/ipe_header/">
          <front>
            <title>Internet Protocol Extension Header</title>
            <author/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDS_AOS" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/732x0b4.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>AOS Space Data Link Protocol, Blue Book 732.0-B-4</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2021" month="October"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDS_TM" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/132x0b3.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>TM Space Data Link Protocol, Blue Book 132.0-B-3</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2021" month="October"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDS_TC" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/232x0b4e1c1.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>TC Space Data Link Protocol, Blue Book 232.0-B-4</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2021" month="October"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDS_PROX1" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/211x0b6e1.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Proximity-1 Space Link Protocol—Data Link Layer, Blue Book 211.0-B-6</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2020" month="July"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDS_USLP" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/732x1b2s.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Unified Space Data Link Protocol, Blue Book 732.1-B-2</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2021" month="October"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="wasm" target="https://github.com/webassembly/spec">
          <front>
            <title>WebAssembly Specifications</title>
            <author>
              <organization>World Wide Web Consortium(W3C)</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ioag" target="https://www.ioag.org/Public%20Documents/Lunar%20communications%20architecture%20study%20report%20FINAL%20v1.3.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>The Future Lunar Communications Architecture, Report of the Interagency Operations Advisory Group</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Lunar Communications Architecture Working Group, Interagency Operations Advisory Group</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2022" month="January"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ioag-mars" target="https://www.ioag.org/Public%20Documents/MBC%20architecture%20report%20final%20version%20PDF.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>The Future
                Mars Communications Architecture, Report of the Interagency Operations Advisory Group
                </title>
            <author>
              <organization>Mars and Beyond Communications Architecture Working Group, Interagency Operations Advisory Group</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2022" month="February"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="curl" target="https://curl.se">
          <front>
            <title>Curl</title>
            <author/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDSWEB" target="https://ccsds.org">
          <front>
            <title>Consultative Committee for Space Data Systems</title>
            <author>
              <organization>CCSDS</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="quic-sim" target="https://deepspaceip.github.io/meetings/ietf120/ietf120-deepspaceip-simulation-results.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Deep Space IP:
            Some simulation results</title>
            <author fullname="Marc Blanchet" initials="M." surname="Blanchet">
              <organization>Viagenie</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="July" year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>This work started by reassessing the use of the whole IP stack in the context of deep space discussed in <xref target="I-D.many-deepspace-ip-assessment"/> where early contributors are acknowledged.</t>
      <t>This document and its underlying work has been reviewed and discussed by many, who have provided valuable feedback and comments, including disagreements, and made an overall more solid document. These people are, in no specific order: Padme Pillay-Esnault, Marius Feldmann, Britta Hale.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
